mark that was so incredibly powerful and
how many things got wrapped in tied
together and actually sequenced in that
time was really mind-blowing for me
watching starting with the evolutionary
story of universe that Barbara shared
and really sharing it as a love story
and then taking that into unique cells
and then unique self Symphony and
foreshadowed in the future in that way
is just a really clear and beautiful
progression and I think I felt that it
really took the evolutionary story the
barber chairs are powerfully last time
and got a deep in it in meaningful ways
and the two major parts that I really
heard is this outrageous love is the
driver of universe and the unique self
and all the elements of both of those
and to comment on the outrageous love
that the evolutionary story has in
interior that there's consciousness that
goes with it is a huge step right from
materialism and then that consciousness
has its own interior the interior of the
interiors you called it which is love
that the evolution side of the inside
impulse is driving that it's a very
powerful beautiful story and in
different words the way I was thinking
about it is that emergence and evolution
is really driven it or described by
emergence fundamentally novel things and
that emergence comes from synergy
synergy the whole being more than sum of
its parts is really what drives
fundamental novelty coming about and
that synergy comes from relationship and
comes from togetherness which is driven
by attractive forces and that love as
the great attractive force if we want to
think of it that way we have we have the
physical attractive forces in the
interior corollary of that as love and
that at the deepest level the interior
and exterior are mirrors of the same
writing exactly so that really we have
this Universal attractive force driving
relationship driving synergy driving
emergence driving evolution it's just
such a powerful frame for the whole
universe story yeah no no complete
Daniel I mean let's look at it you know
just make it kind of complete practical
Barbara Daniel mark sitting here synergy
so what as soon as you mean as you say
energy means that the whole is greater
than the sum of its parts what allows
the three of us to sit here we love each
other if we didn't love each other we
couldn't do this it wouldn't work
but if we love each other we create a
synergy and then we actually moved the
evolutionary story forward and if any of
us would egoic Li claim this story right
then we couldn't move it forward now at
the same time we can't disappear so
Barbara Wright reminds it reminds us not
as an ego as a unique self and I coined
the term conscious evolution because
she's saying this was Barbara Ness and
that's actually divine pride it's the
delight of being unique self and I went
and I developed eniac self and Daniel's
gonna write so we don't disappear we
actually shine but in our shining we're
radically loving each other which is the
process of the cosmos so that process
that's happening right here is happening
all the way up and all the way down
that's the synergy that drives evolution
and that creates a synergy is really
another word for evolutionary level
outrageous love beautiful right
and the little distinction just tagging
then I wanna hear Barbara's thoughts on
it is that synergy of things that are
identical is much less interesting right
energy of things that are differentiated
and so it's this differentiate and
integrate process that leaves a little
emergence exactly I want to hear Barbara
but there's so much to talk about that
Barbara Barbara talk well I mean to say
but the the thing that has always amazed
me about evolution is it's the word
allurement mmm that the entire process
is built on attraction you know from
quarks to subatomic particles all the
way through to us sitting here talking
and I wanted to bring up a thought that
I forgot to mention but then I want to
relate it to what you said and it was my
groping for the definition of
evolutionary consciousness mmm it is
really inherent in what you're saying
and I coined three ease the first
element of evolutionary consciousness
would be the eternal the one the source
the infinite the second E is embody
because the amazing thing is each of us
embodies from the subatomic particle all
the way on up to the you know the
reptilians that mainly in the knee
we are embodying the entire story
sitting here so if this is outrageous
love the story is outrageous love and
then the next word is emergence emerge
so eternal embody emerge because we're
always that love is creative
it's emergent its emergent and then the
last thought here would be is the
definition of God actually I've been
groping for weight I've been reading
Iliad le o--'s who work on the emergent
Christ she's a Catholic and she doesn't
she's out doing all the Catholics with
new cosmology I mean she brings them all
up to up to the up to bat there but she
says that at the origin of the universe
she sees God and Christ I said to her
how could you see Christ at the origin
of the universe she said since it's a
vector of love and it's heading for love
so I guess my question in here is what's
at the origin mmm ya know it's beautiful
it's beautiful I mean Christ is unique
self you know whether we're gonna use a
term like Christ or whatever in church
whatever that one way is Christ is the
unique self and the unique self is is as
you talked about unconscious to
conscious evolution I like to talk about
unconscious to conscious uniqueness so
when Christ wakes up the uniqueness
wakes up but that strange attractor was
always there and you you find your eros
and maybe that's the fourth II before
thee is erotic yeah erotic not a sexual
sense with exiled eros to the sexual
it's the emergence is erotic right the
emergence itself is erotic it's
energized and alive and passionate and
pulsating and right and everything that
erotic could possibly be so unique self
is the erotic incarnation and unique
self has erotic intelligence right it
finds its way to new creativity and
two new synergies and again right
synergies to really simple word don't
get lost in that word synergy just means
as daniel said right when the parts come
together they form a new whole that's
eros it's a new birth yes and the great
thing about since energy and Sentra P is
it uses chaos rate and entropy or
disorder right for higher order and I
like to bring that in because we're in
so much chaos today that if you see it
as they as the ground out of which the
Neuse entropy is taking place in through
the outrageous love that's yeah that you
could see truly the design even in the
disasters yeah that's that's so
important I mean it's disasters and then
here from Daniel but you talk about
chaos you know you never Lucien with
others randomness randomness is one of
the structures of evolution but the
mistake is when people identify
randomness with a universe that's not
purposeful right randomness is then
interpreted as a universe without telus
randomness is a mechanism of the
university right it's not the nature of
the universe
and that distinction changes the game
and both to talk of course more about
that that was a big two sentences that's
responding it see I'm really unpacking
what we're all saying randomness is a
method but that method is actually part
of the method of a larger right tell us
to the universe yes I just do a little
thought in there is the rate of freedom
that if there weren't randomness it
would be robotic universe so the you
might say the the risk that the creative
intention takes is all this randomness
coming together in higher and higher
order right now it's so so beautiful and
the risk of randomness is driven always
by love because we always risk freedom
we rescue face we love if I love you I'm
willing to step back and allow you to
choose even when you choose against me
cuz I love you so much
to fit into the context of right now I'm
biting my tongue so hard on the
relationship between entropy and synergy
and their role in that relation right
right so important so tag that cuz we're
gonna
to it later in the course and just
explain to him what entropy means so
someone doesn't feel like they got lost
the nature of or the principle by which
things disorder breakdown and so as
Barbara mentioned last time there's this
kind of emergence through emergency
there's emergency as a driver of
evolution and we're tagging it more now
and so we're gonna really see how the
ways that humanity has been that have
caused the problems that we're dealing
with now we're actually the solutions to
previous problem right so there is a
kind of evolutionary necessity and
innocence in it and at the and so we
don't have to begrudge the past and we
can't continue it and to be able to
recognize the evolutionary relevance and
the relevance of transforming at the
same time is really powerful it's
critical and you before you make your
point which I'm dying to hear just for
the kind of really rigorous listeners
let's make a distinction between
randomness which is a mechanism of
evolution and disaster which is often
emergent from human choice which comes
from right the possibility of human
freedom so there's two kind of
structures in the universe one is the
process of randomness that happens as an
evolutionary mechanism which moves
towards you know natural selection sex
sexual selection moral selection for the
precise listeners and then there's the
disaster right the crisis that creates
new opportunity which are two different
structures of the cosmos let's just kind
of hold them yeah distinguish them yeah
different and deeply related and will be
different again we have to have a whole
rank this is the whole story right right
this is exciting so this is the second
major thing that you share that really
has to do with unique self the first
time I ever heard about you and I didn't
even really pay attention to your name I
just saw it like five years before we
met and I didn't know who you were I saw
something there was a talk you're giving
called challenging the dogma of oneness
or something like this and it had this
just a little brief blurb on unique self
and it hit me as so critically necessary
important profound a teaching because
what you're bringing together is utter
interconnectedness and the
differentiated unique role within that
interconnectedness that's what allows
synergy to
meaningful because synergy of one thing
with itself unity of one thing with
itself is not very interesting right
right
the differentiate integrate Drive
novelty that's what's really interesting
and so to say true self and then unique
expression of true self which ends up
leading to a rio nning of obligation as
you like to call it right but not as
dogma as a there's a role I have to play
for University nobody else could play
and if I don't someone won't play it
they'll play their role but universe
will be less if I play it less fully I
mean it would have been otherwise so
there's this you know second-tier kind
of Dharma that it's a duty that's so
beautiful and and almost the part that I
love the most is I have to do that and I
can't do any other and yet I want the
others to occur and so that my heart
doesn't shut down I'm gonna focus on
mine but I also have to trust that
you're going to do yours and I want you
to so rather than compete with you to
keep my heart open I need you to do your
Dharma to your unique self - and I need
Barbara to do hers - and so when you say
that jealousy and competition ends with
uniqueness because you can only compete
on the same metric right when you
realize that you're fundamentally unique
my fullest expression you're metric
could never be compared and yet they're
totally symbiotic and the floor you
expressed your is the better universe I
live in and the mark and express mine it
solves most of the human problems that
exist an exciting social model that it's
just it's just dazzle it really sounds
like a good design yeah right exactly
right right right right no I mean me
maybe that to finish this conversation
to pick up on on this word obligation
which as we've talked about and in the
unique self you know work I stress a lot
because the word obligation you know
kind of makes people contract obligation
I thought we were talking about stuff
that was exciting actually the original
Hebrew the word obligation the word love
is the same word right because actually
have the second tier of consciousness
obligation is the unique incarnation of
you know the love intelligence and and
Michael Beckwith's phrase that that I
love love beauty right that actually
lives in us when that actually happens
that creates obligation in the most
delightful enjoy a sense and it's a wrap
whole sense of joy and to live without
that sense of obligation is to actually
live adrift right to live in a kind of
sea of meaninglessness so to reclaim
obligation as outrageous love and this
synergistic sense and maybe to finish
with just how it's happening right here
cuz it's the most immediate thing you
know I mean Barbra you've done so much
work over so much time and developed so
many pieces and Daniel you're emerging
so beautifully into your work I've said
my whole life doing my work and that we
really get to come together and how all
the pieces fit so beautifully and and
that we're each doing a different piece
of that actually a larger voice emerges
right that doesn't have faced us we
don't just meld into the oneness right
Barbara is barbering right it's
resplendent Daniel's Daniel and Mark is
marking and to be able to actually
incarnate that that is the process of
evolution synergy just happening right
here and you know it's also joining
genius joining genius because unique
right and if you get a good
configuration of joining right then you
get something so wonderfully being born
that's what I feel is yeah yeah yeah
absolutely
I think birth to something new by
joining genius joining genius friends
join genius with us we're gonna come
back to all of these ideas right that
we've kind of thrown into the mix and
deepen right in the future weeks
let's join genius thank you